Guide to the Paul Beckett Papers 1939-1989
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Paul Beckett Papers
1939-1989
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 559
Beckett, Paul Louis, 1913-
5 Linear feet of shelf space 7 boxes
Paul Louis Beckett was Professor of Political Science at Washington State University from 1947 to 1977. The papers of Paul Beckett are made up of correspondence with fellow scholars, consisting mostly of letters of recommendation for former students and colleagues, administrative reports on the Department of Political science, and draft writings on research and teaching of municipal government.
Paul Louis Beckett, Professor of Political Science at Washington State University from 1947 to 1977, was born October 18, 1913, in Warren County, Illinois. He completed a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1935 at Monmouth College, a Master of Arts at the University of Illinois in 1938, and a Doctor of Philosophy at the University of California at Los Angeles in 1949.
During the early 1940s Beckett was employed in municipal government in Los Angeles and also worked in a war-time administrative agency in Washington, D.C. From 1945 to 1947 he was a member of the faculty of the University of New Mexico, and in 1947 he joined the Political Science faculty of Washington State College. His field of special expertise was municipal government; his interests and research also included the politics of organization and reorganization, individual and group behavior in organizations, decision making, leadership and authority, communication, and how to ensure administrative responsiveness and responsibility.
During the 1950s, a time when many colonized countries in the Middle East gained independence, Beckett actively participated in the establishment of municipal governments while teaching at the American University in Beirut. In 1952, Beckett, his wife, and their two young children traveled to Beirut, where he established the Department of Political Science at the American University and taught the history and fundamentals of municipal government.
After returning from Beirut, Beckett extended his administrative duties at Washington State College, serving as chair of the Department of Political Science for eight years. In 1957 he was a public administration consultant to the planning board of the Pakistani government.
In addition to his teaching and administrative activities, Beckett was also an active member of the American Political Science Association, the Pacific Northwest Political Science Association, The American Association of University Professors, and the American Society for Public Administration.
The papers of Paul Beckett are made up of correspondence with fellow scholars, consisting mostly of letters of recommendation for former students and colleagues, administrative reports on the Department of Political science, and draft writings on research and teaching of municipal government.
The papers have been only slightly rearranged from Beckett's original filing system. The collection is arranged in three series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1939-1979
Series 2: Subject Files, 1940-1976
Series 3: Addendum (added materials), 1939-1989. This sequence consists of materials added to the collection after initial processing. It contains correspondence, subject files, and miscellaneous information concerning Washington State College and the city of Pullman.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The Washington State University Libraries received papers of Paul Beckett in two installments (accession numbers UA 1978-08 and MS 1985-44). One group of papers (UA 1987-08) was incorrectly identified as university records at the time of receipt. The two accessions were combined in October 1988.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Beckett, Paul Louis, 1913- -- Archives
Washington State University -- Faculty -- Archives.
Political science -- Study and teaching.
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State); Politics and Politicians
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1939-1979
  - Business correspondence
    - 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1942 (includes curriculum vitae) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - 1951 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - 1951 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1953 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - 1953 (July-August) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - 1955 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - 1955 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1956 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1954 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - 1957 (January-September) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1957 (September-December) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1958 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1958 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
    - 1959 (January-May) (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - 1959 (June-December) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - 1960 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
    - 1960 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - 1961 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
    - 1961 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - 1962 (January-August) (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - 1962 (September-December) (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - 1963 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 46-47)
    - 1963 (July-December) (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - 1964 (January-June) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - Richard Butler, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Wallace E. Caldwell, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - John D. Blacken, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Judith Carr, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Jawad Dajani, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Earl Darrah, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Jerry Davis, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Jeanne Howe, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - William L. Jackson, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - John Junker, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - William H. Lee, 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Timothy Manring, 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Stanley G. McClure, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Donna McIntrie, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Lawrence K. Muns, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Charles S. Oldham, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Howard Payne, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Catherine Peat, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Roger D. Reed, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Fred Segrest, 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Ann Stuart Sheldon, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Thomas Franklin Stinson, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Celeste Sunderland, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Karl Van Asselt, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Washington State College students' correspondence
    - 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - 1954-1958 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 80-80.1)
    - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 93)
- Series 2: Subject Files, 1940-1976
    - Ad hoc Committee on Dedication of Johnson Tower, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - American Assembly on State Government, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 95-98)
    - American Assembly paper on Washington, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 99-100)
    - American Association of University Professors, WSC (WSU) chapter, 1954-1973 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - American Society for Public Administration
    - Conference reporting committee, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Reporting committee correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 103-105)
    - Inland Empire chapter, 1956-1969 (Box 2, Folder 106-109)
    - National conference, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Annals book review, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Annals book review, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - Associated Students of Washington State University and Communist speakers, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Beckett as Coordinator of Graduate Studies and Graduate Students, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Beckett as Dad's Day King, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 115-117)
    - Beckett Goes to Beirut, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - Beckett Goes to Pakistan, 1957 (plus: The Confessions of a "Biased Professor," by H. Paul Castleberry) (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Beckett's Training and Experience, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Budget Requests, History and Political Science, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - "Bureaucracy and Democracy," 1952 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - "Civil Service in Beverly Hills, California," 1940 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - College Committee On Review, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - Committee for Redistricting Washington State, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Crowell Commonwealth Series, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Department of History and Political Science Enrollment, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Department of History and Political Science newsletter, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Department of History and Political Science newsletter, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Division of Governmental Studies and Services, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - Evaluation of Hugh Bone's Executive Article for a model State Constitution, 1968 April (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Faculty Status Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Faculty Status Committee, annual and treasurer's reports, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Faculty Status Committee, Senate Review (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Faculty Service Reports, 1947-1969 (Box 2, Folder 135-136)
  - From Wilderness to Enabling Act, The Evolution of A State of Washington, by Paul Beckett, 1968
    - Chapters 1-3 (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - Chapter 4 (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - Appendix (Box 3, Folder 139)
    - Galley proof (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - Fulbright to Egypt, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Graduate Student Committees and Examinations (Work Completed)
    - 1948-1970 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 143)
    - Illinois Law Review, 1942-1946. (Box 3, Folder 144)
    - Institute of World Affairs, University of Southern California, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 145)
    - J. Kimbrough Owen Memorial Fund, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 146)
    - Judicial Review of Labor Legislation in California, 1880-1910; 1961 (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - Legislation and Representation: Papers and Articles, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 148-149)
    - "Letter from Beirut," 1952 (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - Los Angeles Town Hall Constitution, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - Los Angeles Town Hall Municipal and County Government, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1958 (Box 3, Folder 153-159)
    - Mock Political Convention, WSU, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - Mock Political Convention, WSU, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 161)
    - Pacific Northwest Assembly on Federal Government and Higher Education, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 162)
    - Pacific Northwest Library Association project, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 163)
    - Pacific Northwest Panel on State Government, Moscow, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 164)
    - Pacific Northwest Political Science Association panel on honors programs, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 165)
    - Pacific Northwest Political Science Association presidency, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 166)
    - Pacific Northwest Quarterly book review, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - Personnel Administration in Santa Monica, CA, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 168)
    - Phi Kappa Phi, WSU Chapter, President's file, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 169)
    - Phi Kappa Phi Scholarship Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 170)
    - Phi Sigma Alpha National Council, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 171)
    - Political Science 440 final course schedule, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 172)
    - Political Science 445 evaluation and incentives, undated (Box 3, Folder 173)
    - Political Science 592: Dr. Beckett's Last Seminar, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 174)
    - "Politics, Personalities, and Pensions, Final Report on Santa Monica Personnel Administration," 1940 (Box 3, Folder 175)
    - Pre-law, Political Science Department, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 176)
    - Presidential Address, Eleventh annual meeting Pacific Northwest Political Science Association, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 177)
    - Project on State Government, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 178)
    - Public Administration Training as Technical Assistance: Some Further Observations Based on Experience in Beirut (Box 3, Folder 179)
    - Public Opinion Laboratory, WSC, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 180)
    - Public Opinion poll on Washington State Government, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 181)
    - "Quest for Quality Conference," University of Washington, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 182)
    - Research Council Presidency, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 183)
    - Review of Khadduri and Liebesney, Law in the Middle East, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 184)
    - Labor Legislation in California, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 185)
    - Reviews of Henry Goodnow on The Civil Service of Pakistan, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 186)
    - Society for International Development, Korean research project, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 187)
    - Speeches, 1940-1952 (Box 3, Folder 188)
    - Speeches, 1952-1971 (Box 3, Folder 189)
    - Student-Faculty questionnaires, University of New Mexico, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 190)
    - Technical Assistance article for Washington State Review, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 191)
    - "The California Supreme Court and Early Efforts at Labor Legislation," Chapter 12, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 192)
    - The Concept of Evolution in Peter Kropotkin's Anarchism: A Study of Revolutionary Theory, by Paul Beckett, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 193)
    - "The Conflict between North and South," talk for USC Institute of World Affairs, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 194)
    - "The Executive as Ropedancer," talk at the University of British Columbia, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 195)
    - "The International Law of Aerial Navigation," 1940 (Box 3, Folder 196)
    - "The Professional School and World Affairs," regional conference, University of Oregon, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 197)
    - Third annual Institute on World Affairs, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 198)
    - University of New Mexico, undated (Box 4, Folder 199)
    - Washington Political Science Association Executive Council, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 200)
    - "Washington State's Lawmakers," Washington Political Quarterly, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 201)
    - "Washington State's New Merit System Law" (manuscript), 1962 (Box 4, Folder 202)
    - Washington State University Institute of World Affairs, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 203)
    - Water Research Center project, Harvey Doerkson, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 204)
    - Western Governmental Research Association second annual conference, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 205-207)
    - Western Political Quarterly, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 208)
    - Western Political Science Association, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 209)
    - Whitman County, WA, government, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 210)
    - Whitman County manuscripts and working papers, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 211)
    - Woodrow Wilson Award Committee, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 212)
    - Workshop for middle managers talk, Fairchild Air Force Base, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 213)
- Series 3: Addendum (added materials), 1939-1989
  - Correspondence, Washington State College Department of History and Political Science
    - 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 214)
    - 1965 (Box 5, Folder 215)
    - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 216)
    - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 217)
    - 1968 (Box 5, Folder 218)
    - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 219)
    - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 220)
    - 1971 (Box 5, Folder 221)
    - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 222)
    - 1973 (Box 5, Folder 223)
    - 1974 (Box 5, Folder 224)
    - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 225)
    - 1976 (Box 5, Folder 226)
    - 1977 (Box 5, Folder 227)
  - Correspondence, personal
    - I. Cecil Asfour, 1958-1963 (Box 6, Folder 228)
    - Clarence A. Berdahl, 1939-1949 (Box 6, Folder 229)
    - Ronald Beyensee, 1956, 1958, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 230)
    - Paul and Ben Booz, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 231)
    - Carol F. Clark, 1960-1961, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 232)
    - Dr. and Mrs. Wilson Martindale Compton, 1957-1967 (Box 6, Folder 233)
    - Mike and Ethel Crowe, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 234)
    - Earl Davis, 1939-1955 (Box 6, Folder 235)
    - Melvin Davis, 1960-1974 (Box 6, Folder 236)
    - Tom Donnelly, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 237)
    - Pierre Ecoiffier, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 238)
    - Ernst W. Gohlert, 1966-1975 (Box 6, Folder 239)
    - J.A.C. Grant, 1939, 1941, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 240)
    - Charles B. Hagan, 1938-1978 (Box 6, Folder 241)
    - Robert J. Harris, 1939-1949 (Box 6, Folder 242)
    - Bruce and Lolly Haston, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 243)
    - Jack Holmes, 1947-1955 (Box 6, Folder 244)
    - Robert and JoAnn Lampman, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 245)
    - William and Eliza Landeen, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 246)
    - Mr. and Mrs. C.B. Martin, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 247)
    - Art and Bertha O'Neil, 1943, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 248)
    - Walter C. Schnackenberg, 1954-1973 (Box 6, Folder 249)
    - Maxine Guse Semmel, 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 250)
    - Harold Scheffelman, 1955-1959 (Box 6, Folder 251)
    - Foster Sherwood, 1948-1956 (Box 6, Folder 252)
    - Clyde F. Snider, 1939-1971 (Box 6, Folder 253)
    - Thor Swanson, 1951-1964 (Box 6, Folder 254)
    - Dave and Olga Mary Wilder, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 255)
    - American University of Beirut students, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 256)
  - Subject files
    - Ad hoc committee on General Graduation Requirements, 1962-1964 (Box 6, Folder 257)
    - The American Political Science Association Conference, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 258)
    - Beckett-Lamp Water Research Center grant, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 259)
    - County Government Across the Nation, Chapter 5 (annotated typescript) (Box 7, Folder 260)
    - Haynes Foundation, Los Angeles, 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 261)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and printed ephemera, 1960-1973 (Box 7, Folder 262-272)
    - Pacific Northwest Political Science Association, 1958-1981 (Box 7, Folder 273)
    - Potential article, research on Washington legislative committees, 1951-1959 (Box 7, Folder 274)
    - Potential article, research on birth places of Washington legislators, 1889-1989 (Box 7, Folder 275)
    - Research Studies, 1951-1959 (Box 7, Folder 276)
    - "The Role of the Representative Assembly in a Democracy," 1939 (Box 7, Folder 277)
    - United States Bureau of Budget, 1949-1953 (Box 7, Folder 278)
    - Western Government Research Association, Conference Proceedings, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 279)
    - Western Political Science Association conference programs, 1951-1974 (Box 7, Folder 280)